Guide to the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies records, 1965-1981
University Archives Duke University
Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies records 1965-1981
Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
8 Linear Feet 8,000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
Contains the records of the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, a cooperative institute established in 1963 under the auspices of the Duke University-University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Cooperative Program in the Humanities. Also contains materials relating to the Duke University Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies. Types of materials include correspondence, grant proposals, budgets, invitations, rosters, announcements, minutes, local publications, and some conference papers. Major subjects include the Duke University Cooperative Program in the Humanities, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill faculty, Duke University faculty, the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, the Southeastern Renaissance Conference, university cooperation in North Carolina, renaissance study and teaching, and humanities study and teaching. Materials range in date from 1965 to 1981.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Acquired; 1976; 76-187
Gift; 1978; 78-153
Gift; 1980; 80-36
Gift; 1980; 80-218
Gift; 1981; 81-106
Historical Note
The Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies was a cooperative scholarly institute established in 1963 under the auspices of the Duke University-University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Cooperative Program in the Humanities. During the summers, the institute's members presented five-week seminars in a classroom setting. The location of the institutes alternated between the campuses of Duke University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. They were coordinated by a joint committee of faculty members from each university. These institutes drew scholars from colleges and universities throughout the United States and provided a forum for intense study and teaching. Beginning in 1968, the joint committee initiated a fund-raising effort for continuation of the institutes.
In 1972, the National Endowment for the Humanities approved an additional funding request to support the institutes for the summers of 1974-1976 based on the stipulation that by 1977 the institutes would be funded entirely by the two sponsoring campuses.
While summer institutes were held through the summer of 1979, the joint committee was not able to secure a commitment of permanent funding from either Duke or UNC-Chapel Hill. Plans for the 1980 Institute were canceled due to the lack of funding and the committee began a new search for continuing support. The Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies has not been active since 1980.
Many scholars and coordinators of the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies were also affiliated with the Southeastern Renaissance Conference, an annual conference established cooperatively by Duke University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1943. Renaissance studies continue at Duke University at the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, an interdisciplinary, degree-granting program.
Collection Overview
Contains materials of the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies and the Duke University Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies. Materials mostly concern session planning and relations with the Cooperative Program in the Humanities. Types of materials include correspondence, grant proposals, budgets, invitations, rosters, announcements, minutes, local publications, and some conference papers. Materials range in date from 1965 to 1981.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Civilization, Medieval -- Study and teaching (Higher).
Cooperative Program in the Humanities.
Duke University -- Faculty -- History.
History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States.
Humanities -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Southern States
North Carolina -- Intellectual life.
Renaissance -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Southern States
Renaissance -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina.
Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies
Southeastern Renaissance Conference
University cooperation
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Faculty -- History.
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Seminar background materials, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Participant correspondence, 1965-1968
  - General planning materials, 1965-1968
  - Planning materials for the first summer institute, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation correspondence
  - Duke University Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, student studies and lectures, 1973-1976
  - Institute general history, ca. 1963 (Box 3)
  - Research awards winners, 1970
  - Institute evaluations
  - Cooperative Program in the Humanities minutes, 1967-1968
  - Junior and Senior fellow invitations and correspondence (bulk 1974)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 4)
  - Session planning materials
  - Calendars
  - Financial materials
  - Applicant orientation materials
  - NEH grant applications, correspondence, and reports, 1971-1976
  - Ford Foundation grant materials, ca. 1974
  - Program evaluations, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976
  - General session planning materials, 1975-1976
  - Joint Committee, Cooperative Program in the Humanities minutes, 1963-1969
  - Correspondence with institute instructors, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Participant lists, 1978
  - Conference papers, 1973
  - NEH report materials, 1976-1978
  - Summer institute session planning materials, 1965-1968
  - Meeting minutes, 1978
  - Financial materials, 1978
Related Material
Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Report ... the Cooperative Program in the Humanities, 1963-1969 [378.73 C778R]
University Archives, Duke University.